"How Much Caffeine Is
Safe During Pregnancy?"
Is caffeine safe
during pregnancy?
Pregnancy greatly reduces our
ability to metabolize caffeine.
For example, in a typical adult,
caffeine blood levels
fall by about half,
also known as the "half-life",
in five hours.
As you reach mid-pregnancy,
that time doubles,
and by the time you reach
the third trimester,
it can take 15 hours, or more,
to reduce caffeine
to a similar level.
At the same time, fatigue is one
of the most common complaints
of pregnant women.
Couldn't a little
extra energy boost
from slowly metabolizing
caffeine be a good thing?
Unfortunately, caffeine readily
passes through the placenta,
and if you think expecting moms
metabolize slowly,
babies have even less capacity
to metabolize caffeine,
with a half-life of 80 hours;
that's more than three days!
But, to what effect?
In pregnancy,
is caffeine a friend or foe?
Respected authorities,
including the
World Health Organization,
the European
Food Safety Authority,
and The American College
of Obstetrics and Gynecology
have guidelines for a
"positive pregnancy experience,"
including restricting
caffeine intake
to reduce the risk
of pregnancy loss
and low birth weights.
Higher caffeine intake
pre-pregnancy
is associated with higher risk
of miscarriages,
and higher intake
during pregnancy
is associated
with low birth weight,
so the World Health Organization
suggests reducing consumption
to less than 300 mg
of caffeine a day,
whereas the
European Food Safety Authority
suggests 200 mg per day
may be the safety limit,
in agreement with The American College
of Obstetrics and Gynecology.
That comes out to about
two cups (480 ml)
of brewed coffee a day,
assuming that's
your sole caffeine source.
Since those guidelines
were issued,
this study of 2,000 moms
found that even just a half cup
of coffee (120 ml) or so a day
was associated with
a lower birth weight
by about two ounces (60 g),
which suggests that exposure to
even less than 100 mg of caffeine
may be associated with
decreased fetal growth.
The question is,
is it cause and effect?
Is there something
about caffeine that's doing it,
or something about
caffeine drinkers?
You can't know unless
you put it to the test.
Or, in this case,
do a Mendelian
randomization study,
which is kind of a proxy for
a randomized controlled trial.
Since due to the luck
of the draw with genes,
some people randomly
have a tendency
to drink more or less coffee
throughout their life.
And it did not find
a strong relationship
between genetic determinants
of coffee consumption
and these adverse outcomes,
so it isn't clear if the links
that have been found are causal.
There appears to have only been
one randomized controlled trial
that tried to test it.
More than a thousand
coffee-drinking pregnant women
were randomized
to caffeinated coffee or decaf
at an average of four months
into their pregnancies.
To improve compliance,
they were just asked
to switch to the provided coffee
without being prescribed
a specific caffeine intake.
But, thanks to
the complimentary coffee,
the women in the decaf group
ended up consuming 200 fewer mg
of caffeine a day
than those in the
caffeinated coffee group.
So, in the end, the decaf group
complied with the recommendation
of getting less than
200 to 300 mg of caffeine a day,
and the caffeine group did not.
Was there any difference
in birth weight
or length of pregnancy
between the two?
No.
Is it possible the women
were all getting more
than some threshold amount?
We don't know.
I'm sympathetic
to the view that says,
"Look, the need for caution
is compelling."
So, we should err
on the side of caution,
and tell women
contemplating pregnancy,
or who are pregnant,
to avoid it completely.
But women should realize
that the evidence
implicating caffeine
in birth outcomes
is far from settled.